考虑加入实验物理学行业的同学们
So you are considering going into experimental physics,
我的大门永远向你们敞开
My door is always open.
另外我要再次道歉 可能我的实验不怎么成功
Once again, I'm sorry that the demonstration didn't quite work out,
但我们现在知道 你不小心把斯奈普桃汁
But now we know what happens when you accidentally spill
掉进氦氖激光器的时候会发生什么了
Peach snapple into a helium neon laser.
简单来说就是  别这么干
Short answer is... don't.
现在我们来介绍一下理论物理系
And now to tell you about the theoretical physics department
有请谢尔顿·库珀博士
Is dr. sheldon cooper.
库珀博士
Dr. cooper?
别叫我
Forget it.
稍等
Excuse me.
谢尔顿  我们都商量好了
Sheldon, we both agreed to do this.
别浪费时间
It's a waste of time.
我还不如给一群拉布拉多狗
I might as well explain the laws of thermodynamics
讲讲热力学定律呢
To a bunch of labradoodles.
你再不出来 我就不带你去动漫书店
If you don't do this, i won't take you to the comic book store.
你们好
Hello.
顺便说一句  你的激光器不错
Nice work with the laser, by the way.
看见你们朝气蓬勃的脸庞
Looking out at your fresh young faces,
我回想起了我决定步入学术道路的那一刻
I remember when I too was deciding my academic future
那时我还是个卑微的研究生
As a lowly graduate student.
忘了说  我14岁
Of course, I was 14.
不过我已经取得了你们大多数人
And I'd already achieved more than most of you
望尘莫及的成就  虽然我九点上床
Could ever hope to, despite my 9:00 bedtime.
现在  这个屋子里可能有一两个人
Now, there may be one or two of you in this room
具备学好理论物理学的基本素质
Who has what it takes to succeed in theoretical physics.
即使可能你们学成了之后
Although, it's more likely that you'll spend
只是拿来教五年级的小学生
Your scientific careers teaching fifth graders
要做一个纸壳模型火山
How to make papier mache volcanoes
要怎么使用碳酸氢钠火山岩
with baking soda lava.
感谢老天
Oh, good god.
简单来说
In short--
如果谁告诉你们你们有朝一日
Any one who told you that you would someday be able
能在物理学上有所建树
To make any significant contribution to physics,
那完全是个残忍的笑话  太残忍了
Played a cruel trick on you, a cruel trick indeed.
有问题吗
Any questions?
当然没有
Of course not.
我为科学的未来流泪
I weep for the future of science.
现在请允许我失陪了 新一期蝙蝠侠出版了
Now if you'll excuse me, the latest issue of batman is out.
走吧  莱纳德
Come, leonard.
现在看来  那个激光器实验还不错吧
Laser demonstration's looking pretty good now, huh?
《生活大爆炸》
第二季  第06集
我喜欢每年的这个时候
I love this time of the year.
落叶漫天飞舞 秋高气爽
The leaves are turning, there's a bracing chill in the air.
还有  校园里一整群女生
Plus there's a whole new crop of female grad students
开始长刚刚好的秋膘
About to put on just enough winter weight
让她们看起来既寒酸又易推倒
To make them needy and vulnerable.
就是这样  宝贝  再来一份奶酪饼
That's right, honey, have another calzone.
爸爸等着你
Daddy can wait.
大学里没有规定 不能和研究生约会吗
Isn't there a university policy against dating graduate students?
没有  只要你搭得上讪  你就可以约一个
No, if you can talk to them, you can ask them out.
妈的  陷阱真是无处不在
Damn, there's always a catch.
你们好
Hey, guys.
你好  莱斯利
Hey, leslie.
傻蛋  我听说你昨晚把一个研究生恶心吐了
So, dumbass, I heard you made a grad student throw up last night.
事实才是伸到那些喜欢道听途说者的嗓子眼里
The truth can indeed be a finger down the throat
让你呕吐的那根手指头
Of those unprepared to hear it.
不过我干嘛要跟二流智商的人解释这些呢
But why should I cater to second-rate minds?
因为一流智商的人叫你傻蛋
Because first-rate minds call you "dumbass"?
是吗  噢
Oh, yeah? well...
你这个人真刻薄
You're a mean person.
打扰了  库珀博士
Excuse me, dr. cooper,
我是拉蒙娜·诺维茨基
I'm ramona nowitzki.
我昨晚上旁听了你的讲话
I was at your talk last night.
我觉得你实在是个天才
I think you're just brilliant.
大家都这么认为
That is the prevailing opinion.
我现在确实要吐了
Oh, now I'm gonna throw up.
霍华德·沃罗威茨  工程系
Howard wolowitz, department of engineering,
国际空间站废液处理系统的 设计师之一
Co-designer of the international space station's liquid waste disposal system.
没兴趣
Ew.
库珀博士  你发表的每一篇文章我都读过
Dr. cooper, I've read everything you've published.
我尤其赞成你那篇如何取得
I especially liked your paper on grand unification
线形网状聚合物的大统一理论的论文
Using string-network condensates
我很好奇你是怎么发现
And were wondering how you determined
三维线形网能够形成一张图
That three-dimensional string-nets provided
同时涵盖费米子 和定量波色子的
A unified picture of fermions and gauge bosons?
奇迹啊  一只有智慧的拉布拉多犬
Amazing, an intelligent labradoodle.
你可以叫我伍夫
Woof.
事实是我马上就能突破
The fact is I'm quite close to a breakthrough
中微子如何从线形网聚合物中显形 这一难题了
In showing how neutrinos emerge from a string-net condensate.
天啊  那我们看物理学宇宙的方式 就彻底改变了
Oh, my god, that would change the way we view the entire physical universe.
我就是在做这个
It's what I do.
其实  我们的平斯金-沃罗威茨 废液处理系统
You know, the pishkin-wolowitz liquid waste disposal system
也震动了一些人
Is turning a few heads as well.
再说一次  没兴趣
Again, ew.
我还想听听 你打算如何增加中微子
You know, I'd love to hear more about how you intend to add neutrinos.
我们什么时候一起喝杯咖啡好吗
Could we get a cup of coffee sometime?
我不喝咖啡
I don't drink coffee.
我喝  爱我  就请我喝一杯乔
I do. I love me a cup of joe.
那  不一定要喝咖啡
Well, it doesn't have to be coffee.
晚餐好嘛
How about dinner?
我是得吃晚餐
I do eat dinner.
好极了  我知道一家非常棒的意大利小餐馆
Great. I know a terrific little italian place.
我不在奇怪的餐馆吃饭
I never eat in strange restaurants.
受不合格的餐具危害生命
One runs the risk of non-standard cutlery.
你确定
Excuse me?
谢尔顿惧怕三尖叉子
Sheldon lives in fear of the three-tined fork.
三尖的不是叉子
Three tines is not a fork.
三尖的是三叉戟
Three tines is a trident.
叉子  可以用来吃饭
Forks are for eating,
三叉戟 只能治理七大洋[海神波塞冬的象征物和武器]
Tridents are for ruling the seven seas.
那我打包带到你家吃怎么样
What if I brought food to your place?
这还差不多
That would be acceptable.
星期一  我吃泰国菜
On mondays, I eat thai food.
泰式炒面和沙茶鸡
Mee krob and chicken sate
多来点暹罗的花生酱
With extra peanut sauce from siam palace.
好吧
You got it.
我知道你住在哪
I already have your address.
真是个好姑娘
What a nice girl.
谢尔顿  你知道刚才发生什么了吗
Sheldon, do you have any idea what just happened?
当然  很明显我有免费的晚餐吃了
Yes. apparently I'm getting a free dinner.
别试了  这东西大概是坏了
Oh, yeah, no, this thing's majorly out of order.
-看  -不好意思
- See? - sorry.
没什么
That's okay.
看来得走楼梯了
Guess I'm taking the stairs.
你到哪间
Where you going?
4楼a
4-a.
你是要去找莱纳德吧
Oh, are you here to see leonard?
不是  库珀博士
No, dr. cooper.
谢尔顿·库珀博士
Dr. sheldon cooper?
我们一起吃晚饭
We're having dinner.
谢尔顿·库珀
Sheldon cooper?
高高瘦瘦的
Tall, thin,
看着像只正在祈祷的大螳螂的那个?
Looks a little like a giant praying mantis?
他很可爱  不是么
He is cute, isn't he?
谢尔顿·库珀
Sheldon cooper?
嗨  莱纳德
Hi, leonard.
嗨  拉蒙娜  请进
Hey, ramona. come on in.
我该把吃的放哪
Thanks. where should I put this?
搁灶台上就行
Uh, the kitchen's fine.
你干啥呢
Hey, what are you doing?
我一定要看看这个
I need to see this. uh-huh.
观众席就在那边
The viewing area's right over there.
谢尔顿  你的妞  约会对象  拉蒙娜来了
Sheldon, your girl... date... person... ramona's here.
你好
Oh, hello.
抱歉我来晚了
Oh, sorry I'm late.
我赶着看你最新论文的草稿来着
I just got so caught up reading the draft of your latest paper.
你喜不喜欢我那个注脚
Did you enjoy the humorous footnote
把镜像对称性形容为
Where I illustrate  mirror-symmetry
光和自己玩网球的比喻
By likening it to the flash playing tennis with himself?
太有意思了
So funny.
我不得不说  一想到你可能把重力引入进去
But the idea that you might be able to incorporate gravity,
就让我浑身兴奋
I have to tell you, I found it  physically exhilarating.
我的假设就是想有这种效果
My hypotheses tend to have that effect.
抱歉  我没带够你朋友的份
I'm sorry I didn't bring enough For your friends.
我以为就我们俩呢
I assumed we were going to be alone.
我们正要走呢
No, we were just going.
去看  对吧
To watch, right?
不  走吧  我们出去了
No, come on, now, we're going out.
别  我们不出声
Oh, come on, we'll be quiet.
走吧走吧
Let's go, let's go.
你们俩
Okay, you two.
玩的高兴点
Have a nice...
不管这算什么
Whatever this is.
伙计们  听着 我知道这和我没关系
Okay, you guys, look, i know this is none of my business,
不过我忍不住要问
But I just... I have to ask--
谢尔顿的取向是什么
What's sheldon's deal?
你说的取向指的是什么
What do you mean "deal"?
你知道的  就是他的取向嘛
You know, like what's his deal?
喜欢女生  男生  仿真娃娃
Is it girls...? guys...? sock puppets...?
老实说  我们的假设是
Honestly, we've been operating under the assumption
他没有取向
That he has no deal.
得了吧  每个人都有的
Come on, everybody has a deal.
不包括谢尔顿
Not sheldon.
这些年来  我们列出了很多假设
Over the years, we've formulated many theories
关于他如何繁殖
About how he might reproduce.
我支持有丝分裂
I'm an advocate of mitosis.
什么意思
I'm sorry?
我相信总有一天谢尔顿吃了足够多的泰国菜
I believe one day sheldon will eat an enormous amount
然后分裂成两个
Of thai food and split into two sheldons.
另一方面  我认为
On the other hand, I think sheldon
谢尔顿处于他这种生物的幼虫阶段
Might be the larval form of his species,
有一天他会结一个茧
And someday he'll spin a cocoon and emerge two months later
两个月后带着翅膀和外骨骼破茧而出
With moth wings and an exoskeleton.
谢谢让我做噩梦
Okay, well, thanks for the nightmares.
想和我们一起出去么
Hey, do you want to hang out with us?
你们几个去干嘛
What are you guys gonna do?
我妈妈晚上做了鸡胸肉
My mom's making a brisket tonight.
带小洋葱的那种
The one with the little onions? mm...
我还有点事
Yeah, I'm busy, so...
晚安
Good night.
这是她的损失  我们走
Her loss. let's go.
鸡胸肉聚会
Brisket party!
鸡呀嘛鸡  胸呀嘛胸
B-to-the-r-to-the-i-s-k...
肉呀嘛肉
To-the-e-to-the-t...
你不吃早饭
Hey, aren't you having breakfast?
吃呀
Yes.
你是不是又在做营养坐药的试验了
Are you experimenting with nutritional suppositories again?
做那实验可不能穿这裤子
Not in these pants.
昨晚和拉蒙娜过的怎么样
So... how'd it go with ramona last night?
好极了 她很聪明  有思想
Oh, great. She's smart, insightful
而且她用她特有的方式  那个  崇拜我
And she has a very unique way of, you know, revering me.
你的菠菜蘑菇鸡蛋卷
Here's your spinach mushroom omelet .
谢谢
Thank you.
有没有人碰过
Did anyone touch it?
他们都带手套啦 我特别小心
Gloves were worn by everyone involved. I was vigilant.
拉蒙娜指出我每天都在餐厅排队上
Ramona pointed out that I've been wasting 20 minutes a day
浪费了20分钟
Standing on cafeteria lines.
这些时间如果能用在攻克
Time which would be better spent
当今的物理学难题该多好啊
Tackling the great physics problems of our day.
拉蒙娜你不用主动攻击那些大的课题
You don't tackle the big issues, ramona.
你要回避之
You fence with them.
以守为攻是也
En garde. riposte.
所言极是
Touche.
早上好
Morning.
嗨  莱斯利
Hi, leslie.
谢尔顿
So, sheldon,
听说你在给史密森尼 傻蛋博物馆整理论文呢
I see you're organizing your papers for the smithsonian museum of dumbassery.
目前没有空缺
There won't be any room
除非他们能把永久馆藏的莱斯利·温克尔请出去
Until they get rid of the permanent leslie winkle exhibit.
精妙
Oh, good one.
你找了个研究生护着你哈
I see you got a grad student to fight your battles for you.
今天就不收你保护费了
I'll let you keep your lunch money today.
库珀博士就要取得重大突破了
Okay, dr. cooper is on the verge of a breakthrough.
如果你想待在这
If you're going to stay,
就必须心怀敬意  别出声
You'll have to be respectful and quiet.
等等我
Wait for me.
你解决了中微子那个问题了么
So have you worked out the neutrino issue?
这就好像改写莫扎特的曲子
Well, to paraphrase mozart,
所有的次原子粒子都已经在那了
All the subatomic particles are there.
我要做的就是给它们排个序
I just have to put them in the right order.
你真幽默
You're so witty.
不是么
Aren't i?
嗨  大家好  有快递给
Hey, guys, this package came for...
库珀博士正在工作
Dr. cooper is working.
我马上就会有新的突破啦
Yes, I'm close to a breakthrough.
好痒
Ooh, it tickles!
不好意思
Sorry.
我的老天
Holy crap on a cracker.
嗨  佩妮
Hey, penny.
嗨  你不会想进去的
Hi. you probably don't want to go in there.
咋了  他们干嘛呢
Why? what are they doing?
那种场景
The only way I could explain it
只可能出现在放着洋娃娃的临床医生的诊室里
Would be in a therapist's office with dolls.
好家伙
Hoo-boy.
库珀博士在工作
Dr. cooper's working.
看得出来
Yeah, I can see that.
谢尔顿  光晕之夜  在库萨帕里家  你来么
Sheldon, halo night, koothrappali's. you coming?
当然  光晕之夜嘛
Oh, yes, it's halo night.
等我擦脚
Let me just dry my tootsies.
你不是要去光晕之夜吧
You're not going to halo night.
是要去
Yes, I am.
今天周三  周三是光晕之夜
It's wednesday. wednesday's halo night.
不是有个伟大的人曾经说过  为科学别无所求
Didn't a great man once say, "science demands nothing less
为科学执着追求  为科学无条件 奉献一生么
"than the fervent and unconditional dedication of our entire lives"?
是有人说过
He did.
那么那个伟大的人是谁呢
And who was that great man?
是我
Me.
抱歉莱纳德
Sorry, leonard.
搞笑  你真不来啦
Seriously? you're not coming?
你也听到了  我无法反驳自己
You heard her. how can I argue with me?
好吧  再次祝你们开心
Okay, well, once again, you guys have a good...
不管干嘛
Whatever this is.
库珀博士  我不得不说
Dr. cooper, I have to tell you
你的朋友拉你后腿了
Your friends are holding you back.
应该这么想  我在带领他们前进
I prefer to think of it as "i'm pulling them forward."
光晕之夜
Halo night?
像你这样极具天赋的人
A man with your intellectual gifts
是不会把整晚都浪费在打游戏上边的
Doesn't waste an evening playing video games.
他周三确实会
He does on wednesdays.
如果他想得诺贝尔奖就不会
Not if he wants a nobel prize.
他是想得
He does want that.
那像他一样极具天赋的人
Does a man with my intellectual gifts
周末玩彩蛋射击么
Play paintball on weekends?
你说呢
What do you think?
惨了
Drat.
现在可以继续工作了吧
Now shall we get back to work?
应该可以
I suppose.
今晚有播《太空堡垒卡拉狄加》
Battlestar galactica  comes on tonight.
我也可以等DVD版
I guess I can wait for the dvd.
还是别再看了
And then never ever watch it.
佩妮  佩妮
Penny! penny!
佩妮
Penny!
谢尔顿  亲爱的  我说过
Sheldon, honey, I've told you,
房子很小
It's a small apartment.
只要敲一次门就行
You only have to knock one time.
求你了  我时间不多
Please, please, I don't have a lot of time.
听着  拉蒙娜终于睡着了
Look, ramona finally dozed off,
我要你帮我甩了她
And I need you to help me get rid of her.
怎么甩了她
Get rid of her how?
我不知道
I don't know,
但显然我陷进某种关系里了
But apparently I'm in some kind of relationship,
而你似乎很擅长结束这种关系
And you seem to be an expert at ending them.
什么
Excuse me?
我见证了一个又一个男人从你屋子离开后就一去不回
I see man after man leaving this apartment never to return.
首先  不是一个又一个男人
Okay, first of all, it is not man after man.
-库珀博士  -把我藏起来
Dr. cooper?! hide me.
把你藏起来
Hide you?
我正式请求进入避难所
I formally request sanctuary.
你怎么没在工作
Why aren't you working?
她分散我的注意力
She distracted me.
我跟你说了  佩妮  我没闲工夫跟你瞎胡闹
I told you, penny, I don't have time for your nonsense.
我有很重要的事要做
I have important things to do.
老天
Oh, man.
我知道怎么回事
I know what's going on here.
真的吗
Really?
那你能给我解释一下吗
Well, then will you explain it to me?
你爱上库珀博士了
You're in love with dr. cooper.
不  不是的
Uh, yeah, no, that's not it.
别狡辩了
Don't try to deny it.
他是个出色的男人
He's a remarkable man,
但你必须放过他
But you have to let him go.
老天爷  没问题
Oh, gee, okay.
我知道很难放手  但他是全世界的礼物
I know it's hard, but he's a gift to the whole world,
我们不能这么自私
And we can't be selfish.
对  他绝对是瑰宝
Yeah, he's a gift all right.
拉钩保证
Sisters?
当然可以
Uh, sure.
拉钩保证
Sisters.
极品级怪胎
Holy crap on a cracker.
谢尔顿
Sheldon?
你在干嘛
What are you doing?!
这是莫尔斯电码
It's morse code.
干嘛
Why?
这样我们才能隔墙通话
So we can communicate through the wall.
我们不正在隔墙通话嘛
We are communicating through the wall.
对  但通话没有加密
Yes, but the communication is not encrypted.
我不懂莫尔斯电码
I don't know morse code.
很简单
It's very simple.
这是A 这是B  这是C
This is a ... This is b ... this is c...
谢尔顿  我不会在凌晨3点 学莫尔斯电码的
Sheldon, I'm not going to learn morse code at 3:00 in the morning!
好吧
All right.
别进来  别进来  别进来
Don't come in here, don't come in here, don't come in here,
别
Don't... oh!
怎么回事
What's going on?
嘘  拉蒙娜正在沙发上睡觉
Shh! ramona's sleeping on the couch.
我知道  她什么时候回家
I know. when is she going home?
她不回家了  问题就在这
Never. that's the problem.
我要你帮忙
I need your help.
你在说什么呢
What are you talking about?
我要调用友情条约里的天网条款
I'm invoking the skynet clause of our friendship agreement.
那个只能在你要我帮你
That only applies if you need me
摧毁你创造的夺取地球的
To help you destroy an artificial intelligence
人工智能机器人时才能用
You've created that's taking over the earth.
行了  别挑剔了
Come on! don't nitpick!
晚安
Good night.
嘘  好吧
Shh. all right.
我调用夺身条款
I'm invoking our body snatchers clause.
夺身条款只能在你要我
The body snatchers clause requires me
帮你摧毁我们知道被外星人
To help you destroy someone we know
附身的人
Who's been replaced with an alien pod.
对  她就在客厅  快上
Yes. she's in the living room. go.
我在这等你
I'll wait here.
谢尔顿  你怎么没睡觉
Sheldon, what are you doing out of bed?
现在  动手
Now! do it!
你得知道  你要好好睡觉
You know you need your sleep
这样你的认知过程
In order for your cognitive processing
才能表现在最佳水平  快走吧
To perform at optimum levels. now come on.
哥斯拉条款
Godzilla clause?
除非她要摧毁东京
Not unless she destroys tokyo.
小人
Rats.
我搞定了
I've got it!
我终于用我的 链性网状结构固化物
I finally reconciled the black hole information paradox
解决了黑洞资讯矛盾
With my theory of string-network condensates!
太不可思议了
It's unbelievable!
这是历史性的改变
It's paradigm-altering.
没有你我根本做不到
And I could not have done it without you.
才怪  我只是给你一点鼓励而已
Oh, please, I just offered a little encouragement.
远不止这些
It was a lot more than that.
你帮我理清杂乱的费米子
You helped me work out the masses of all the fermions
你还帮我磨锤状趾
And you pumiced my hammer toe.
我该怎么报答你
How can I ever repay you?
你能把它命名为库珀诺维茨基定理吗
Well, would you consider naming it the cooper-nowitzki theorem?
谁是诺维茨基
Who's nowitzki?
我就是诺维茨基啊
I'm nowitzki.
你要我分享这份荣誉
Oh, you want me to share credit?
对
Uh-huh.
滚出去
Get out!
你好
Oh, hey, hi.
我要去死
Oh, bite me!
拉钩保证
Sisters?
打扰一下  库珀博士
Excuse me, dr. cooper.
我是凯西·奥布莱恩
I'm kathy o'brien.
我刚刚读完了你的
I just finished reading your paper
利用链性网状结构固化物
Reconciling the black hole information paradox
解决黑洞资讯矛盾的论文
With your theory of string- network condensates,
让我惊叹得喘不过气来
And it just took my breath away.
等我发表了  我可以送你个人工呼吸器
Maybe when I publish it, I'll include an inhaler.
我能跟你交流一下吗
Would you possibly have any time for me to pick your brain?
我想想  今天是周四
Let's see. today's thursday.
周四晚  我吃雅阁墨的比萨饼
Thursday nights, I eat pizza from giacomo's.
加香肠  蘑菇  少量橄榄油
Sausage, mushrooms, light olives.
好极了  我会带到你家去
Great. I'll bring it to your place.
我有你的地址
I have the address.
多好的姑娘
What a nice girl.
谢尔顿  你没看到刚刚发生的事吗
Sheldon, do you see what just happened here?
看到了  我有免费比萨吃了
Yes, I'm getting a free pizza.
看我人气多高
I'm on a roll.
再来一份泰国菜吧
More pad thai, please.
谢尔顿  你已经吃了四份了
Sheldon, you've already had four servings.
你还是吃慢点吧  老兄
You might want to slow down a bit, buddy.
就再吃一口
Just one more bite.
谢尔顿
Sheldon?
谢尔顿  你没事吧
Sheldon, are you okay?
我只是吃撑了
I'm just so... full.
够了  不能再吃泰国菜了
That's it. no more thai food.